Guide to the Joseph Norton Ireland Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Joseph Norton Ireland papers
1770-1902
YCAL MSS 621
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
18.4
(68 boxes)
The collection contains material relating to Ireland's research and writings on American theater and personal papers. Forty-nine volumes in the collection contain clippings, printed ephemera, such as playbills, autograph manuscript material, letters, and other material, as well as lists of theatrical performances and lists and profiles of stage performers. The collection features drafts, proofs, and an extra-illustrated version of Ireland's major publication, Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860.
Ireland, Joseph Norton, 1817-1898
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Ireland Starr in memory of Susan Ireland Starr, 1945.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Joseph Norton Ireland (1817-1898)
Joseph Norton Ireland, one of the major early historians of the American theater, entered his father's business after graduating from high school in his native New York. Leaving the company in 1855 and retiring to Bridgeport, Connecticut, Ireland devoted the rest of his life to studying and writing about the stage. His major work was Records of the New York Stage from 1750–1860 (1866–67), although he also wrote two biographies, Mrs. Duff (1882) and A Memoir of the Professional Life of Thomas Abthorpe Cooper (1888).
Biographical information taken from the Oxford Companion to American Theatre.
Scope and Contents
The Joseph Norton Ireland papers contains material relating to Ireland's research and writing on American theater and personal papers. Forty-nine volumes in the collection contain clippings, printed ephemera, such as playbills, autograph manuscript material, letters, and other material, as well as lists of theatrical performances and lists and profiles of stage performers. Also included are drafts, proofs, and an extra-illustrated version of Ireland's major publication, Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Bound Volumes, 1770-1885. II. Manuscripts, 1852-1880. III. Other Material, 1807-1902.
Theater -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Theater -- New York (State) -- New York -- History; Theater critics -- New York (State) -- New York; Theaters -- New York (State) -- New York -- History; Actors; Scrapbooks; Ephemera (general object genre); Playbills; Photographs; Theater critics -- New York (State) -- 19th century; Ireland, Joseph Norton, 1817-1898; Ireland family; Park Theatre (New York, N.Y.: Park Row)
- Bound Volumes, 1770-1885; Series I; 13.35; (57 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title or supplied heading.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Bound Volumes contains material relating to Joseph Norton Ireland's research on American theater dating from the sixteenth through nineteenth centuries. Scrapbooks and other volumes contain clippings, printed ephemera, including playbills, autograph manuscript material, letters, and other material. There are also lists of theatrical performances and lists and profiles of stage performers. The series features an extra-illustrated version of Ireland's major publication, Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860.
  - "All Dramatic Performances in New York From 1750 to 1848 Vol. 1", undated (Box 1)
  - "All Dramatic Performances in New York From 1750 to 1848 Vol. 2", undated (Box 2)
  - "All Dramatic Performances from ca. 1660 to ca. 1870 Vol.1", undated (Box 3)
  - "All Dramatic Performances from ca. 1660 to ca. 1870 Vol. 2", undated (Box 4)
  - "Biographical Dictionary of New York Theatrical Performers from A.D. 1752... to the Present Time", undated (Box 5)
  - "Characters Performed by Well Known Artists in America Vol. 1", undated (Box 6)
  - "Characters Performed by Well Known Artists in America Vol. 2", undated (Box 7)
  - Diary, 1836-1842 (Box 8)
  - [Fifty Years of a Playgoer's Journal], undated (Box 9)
  - "Garrick and His Contemporaries", undated (Box 10)
  - A Memoir of the Professional Life of Thomas Abthorpe Cooper, Part I, [circa 1888] (Box 11)
    Extra-illustrated version, with engravings, clippings, letters, and autograph manuscript notes
  - A Memoir of the Professional Life of Thomas Abthorpe Cooper, Part II, [circa 1888] (Box 12)
  - "Memorials of Mrs. Duff Collected by Joseph N. Ireland," Vol. I, [circa 1878] (Box 13)
  - "Memorials of Mrs. Duff Collected by Joseph N. Ireland," Vol. II, [circa 1878] (Box 14)
  - "Memorials of Mrs. Duff Collected by Joseph N. Ireland," Vol. III, [circa 1878] (Box 15)
  - "Memorials of Mrs. Duff Collected by Joseph N. Ireland," Vol. IV, [circa 1878] (Box 16)
  - Mrs. Duff, Part I, [circa 1882] (Box 17)
  - Mrs. Duff, Part II, [circa 1882] (Box 18)
  - Mrs. Duff, Part III, [circa 1882] (Box 19)
  - Mrs. Duff, Part IV, [circa 1882] (Box 20)
  - [New York Stage, 1823-1841], 1823-1832 (Box 21)
  - [New York Stage, 1823-1841], 1832-1841 (Box 22)
  - [New York Stage, 1848-1870] (Box 23)
  - [New York Stage, 1848-1870], 1870-1872 (Box 24)
  - [New York Stage, 1848-1870], 1872-1874 (Box 25)
  - [New York Stage, 1848-1870], [circa 1870s] (Box 26)
  - [New York Stage: Actors and Actresses, etc.], [circa 1828-1885] (Box 27)
  - "Newspaper Programmes of the Boston Theatre, 1805 - 1812" (Box 28)
  - "Nightly-Receipts of the Park Theatre From April 18th 1832 To April 5th 1837", 1832-1837 (Box 29)
  - "Nightly-Receipts of the Park Theatre From May 22nd 1837 to April 30th 1842", 1837-1842 (Box 30)
  - "Old New York", undated (Box 31)
  - [Playbills of the Theatre Royal], 1799-1816 (Box 32)
  - Players of the Past, 1564 - 1800, Volume 1, undated (Box 33)
  - Players of the Past, 1564 - 1800, Volume 2, undated (Box 34)
  - Players of the Past, 1564 - 1800, Volume 3, undated (Box 35)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. I, [circa 1867] (Box 36)
    2 v. in 19, extra-illustrated, with engravings, playbills, clippings, letters, photographs, and autograph manuscript notes
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. I-Part II, [circa 1867] (Box 37)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. I-Part III, [circa 1867] (Box 38)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. I-Part IV, [circa 1867] (Box 39)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. I-Part V, [circa 1867] (Box 40)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. I-Part VI, [circa 1867] (Box 41)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. II, [circa 1867] (Box 42)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. II-Part II, [circa 1867] (Box 43)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. II-Part III, [circa 1867] (Box 44)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. II-Part IV, [circa 1867] (Box 45)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. II-Part V, [circa 1867] (Box 46)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. II-Part VI, [circa 1867] (Box 47)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Vol. II-Part VII, [circa 1867] (Box 48)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Supplement-Part I, [circa 1867] (Box 49)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Supplement-Part II, [circa 1867] (Box 50)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Supplement-Part III, [circa 1867] (Box 51)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Supplement-Part IV, [circa 1867] (Box 52)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Supplement-Part V, [circa 1867] (Box 53)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, Index, [circa 1867] (Box 54)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 55)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 56)
  - [Theater in England], [circa 1770-1855] (Box 57)
- Manuscripts, 1852-1880; Series II; 3.13; (8 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series II. Manuscripts contains drafts and proofs for various writings by Ireland relating to the theater, including Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860.
  - [Casts of Various Plays], undated (Box 58)
  - "Catalogue of Plays, 1852, In a Miscellaneous Collection & Longworth's Edition" (Box 58)
  - "Catalogue of Plays Contained in Belle's Octavo...", undated (Box 58)
  - "Catalogue of Theatrical and Other Portraits", undated (Box 58)
  - "Characters Performed by Mr. Peter Richings, With the Number of Their Repetitions", undated (Box 58)
  - "Library Catalogue", undated (Box 58)
  - A Memoir of the Professional Life of Thomas Abthorpe Cooper, draft, undated (Box 58)
  - "Memorials of Mrs. Duff Collected by Joseph N. Ireland in Six Volumes", 1880 (Box 59)
  - "Memorials of Mrs. Duff Collected by Joseph N. Ireland in Six Volumes", 1880; 4 (Box 59)
  - "Memorials of Mrs. Duff Collected by Joseph N. Ireland in Six Volumes", 1880 (Box 60)
  - "Programs of the Royal Theatre Dublin Containing...", undated (Box 60)
  - [Record of Performances Attended, October 31, 1826 to September 6, 1888], undated; 2 (Box 60)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 60)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 61)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, volume 2, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated; 3 (Box 61)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, volume 2, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated; 5 (Box 62)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, volume 2 index, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 63)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, first proofs, corrected, with proofreaders' marks, undated; 3 (Box 63)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, first proofs, corrected, with proofreaders' marks, undated (Box 64)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, second proofs, volume 1, undated; 2 (Box 64)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, second proofs, volume 2, undated; 2 (Box 64)
  - Records of the New York Stage from 1750 to 1860, second proofs, volume 2, undated (Box 65)
- Other Material, 1807-1902; Series III; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Personal Papers.
  Series III. Other Material contains letters to Ireland and various personal papers.
  - Correspondence
    - Ireland, George, 1866-1869 (Box 66)
    - Lockwood, Abraham, 1864-1865; 2 (Box 66)
    - Moore, Charles, 1879 (Box 66)
    - Morrell, T. H., 1861-1874, undated (Box 66)
    - Ryer, F. R., 1886, 1892 (Box 66)
    - Unsorted correspondence, 1855-1898, undated; 3 (Box 66)
  - Personal Papers
    - Acknowledgements, 1860-1893 (Box 66)
    - Calling cards, undated (Box 66)
    - Calling card holder, undated (Box 66)
    - Clippings, 1859-1882, undated (Box 66)
    - Drawing and illustrations, undated (Box 66)
    - Empty envelopes, undated (Box 66)
    - Family documents, 1872-1879, undated (Box 66)
    - Financial records, 1832-1902; 2 (Box 67)
    - Invitations, undated (Box 67)
    - List of portraits, [circa 1850] (Box 67)
    - Manuscript notes and fragments, undated (Box 67)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 67)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 67)
    - Portraits, 1859, 1864 (Box 67)
    - Printed ephemera, 1852-1865, undated (Box 67)
    - Ribbons, undated (Box 67)
    - Satchel, undated (Box 67)
    - Signatures, 1807-1822, undated (Box 67)
    - Top board of box, undated
    - Writings by others, 1844-1884, undated (Box 67)
- Oversize, 1807-1902; 0.08; (1 box)
  - Clippings (In Series III), 1859-1882, undated (Box 68)
  - Family documents (In Series III), 1872-1879, undated (Box 68)
  - Printed ephemera (In Series III), 1852-1865, undated (Box 68)
  - Top board from box (In Series III), undated (Box 68)